The last strike in the Bundestag before the election in just two weeks.
The only topic of the general debate is the situation in Germany.
Broadly enough so that the parties can really get it out again.
The start was still warmly run by the TV duel of Chancellor of the Union,
candidate Merz and Chancellor Scholz.
If we now, despite the low number of asylum seekers, call on the security and order of Germany to be out of control
and therefore we should not have to apply European law,
then other countries will use this argument quite the same,
apart from the fact that it does not exist in court.
That would not be just the end of the European asylum reform,
which Germany is the biggest profit for,
even before it takes effect next year.
That would not just be the end of the European border,
that would be the beginning of the end of the European Union as a legal community.
Have you ever heard the word German vote?
That was the shipwreck in Brussels for the constant detentions of the federal government,
the Federal Republic of Germany, the ministers and the European Council,
because they were so divided in their coalition that they usually did not know
how to vote in Brussels.
A German government has never found so much criticism and so much contempt in Brussels
as this current government.
For this reason, it will be time for them to stop.
And Christoph Meßmacher is following the debate in Berlin for us.
Christoph, how do you perceive the atmosphere at this last speech before the Bundestag election?
I would like to describe it best with a small miniature.
During the speech by Alice Weidel, she complained about the aroused and very loud intercom calls,
especially from the ranks of the Greens.
And Babel-Bas took it with a dry counter to the knowledge and addressed Alice Weidel.
She could deal with her own faction, as far as the volume of the intercom calls is concerned.
It was an intense speech.
It was not what the speeches were about, which was very toxic.
The intercom calls were a bit out of the frame.
There was more whistling in the German Bundestag, which is now very rare.
But overall, the classic positions that were expected have been exchanged again.
For me, interesting were the one or the other side aspects.
We have just heard small excerpts from Scholz and Merz.
What are the two points of focus?
The points of focus that everyone who is interested in politics has noticed in the last days and weeks.
But that is not criticism, but it would be admissible to believe that new positions will be presented today.
As I said, there were some small side notes in the speakers in the role ratio, according to my observation.
What was noticed in the speech of Friedrich Merz was that he was the only one in my perception who addressed the day after the election.
Then there was Glintner and Weidel. What was particularly remarkable for you?
Robert Habeck tried to change the situation a bit, if I may say so.
There is a lot to be said. There is a lot of party criticism, or at least acceptable criticism, on his ten-point plan on migration and asylum.
Today, a letter from the Green Federal Labor Union on peace and migration is expected to be published.
The Green Party is not quite satisfied with what your chancellor candidate has said there.
Robert Habeck used his speech to make it clear that it also has to do with integration on the topic of migration.
There have been a lot of omissions and that this has to change now is the view of the party.
He also tried to address the future topics, including education and climate protection.
Christian Lindner tried it with humor. He saw Olaf Scholz as the next Nobel Prize winner in the ranks of the SPD after Willy Brandt.
He also tried to make it clear that he lost contact with the economy, especially the medium-sized companies.
That's why he was probably the next Nobel Prize winner because he proved that there are parallel universes.
Christoph, many citizens are annoyed by the political disputes that the political parties are having.
What could the parties do to get more sympathy?
To be honest, Chancellor Scholz made a point in his speech.
He said that the debate situation is very exciting, but that on the other hand,
a lot of different positions are clearly defined than in times of the big coalition.
That is certainly a point that many people have to get used to.
The debate has gained a lot of focus.
In my translation, there are very different election programs, very different models of how Germany should be shaped,
or in other words, in which Germany you actually want to live.
And that is actually something advantageous for a democratic debate,
because you can clearly see differences in all political areas.
That is definitely my conviction.
To regain confidence, that means collateral damage, you are certainly right.
The sharpness of the debate and above all the great noise concert of the traffic light until it was over,
has certainly cost confidence.
Friedrich Merz spoke today on February 24, which is the day after the election,
and he has very strongly applied for an alliance from the middle of the democratic parties,
because otherwise he is worried about the country's cohesion in the next four years.
Keyword alliance, so after the election, coalition talks are held.
After these unspoken tones, is there any constructive cooperation at all,
or is there a lot of broken porcelain?
It is broken porcelain, but I am inclined to a pragmatism.
I believe that on March 24 it will be a bit tricky,
then I have to see which personnel then still exists and who then even possible coalition negotiations lead.
But I am very pragmatically strict and believe, as I said,
that the parties will not give the blamage again to receive an invitation from the federal president,
Frank-Walter Steinmeier, to please agree on an alliance.
In this respect, on March 24, some will lick their wounds, others will celebrate themselves as winners.
And then a coalition must be found and the prices are raised.
And then at the end there will be a government.
This will be a tedious, also noisy, process, but I am unwavering at this point.
There will be an alliance, it will be governed.
Thank you, Christoph, for this assessment.
My pleasure.